SR MANUFACTURING ENGINEER

Profile

I'm an Industrial Engineer with experience in continuous improvement, new product introduction, product transfers, process and manufacturing engineering. I have 10 years of experience in the field, I have implemented lean tools like Supermarket, Kanban, 5S, Poka Yokes and I have used tools like VSM, Visual factory, Kaizen.

Skills

Project management

Quality control

Process improvement

Mechanical design/implementation

Operations research

Accomplishments

Quality Control

Improve in process quality in 600 DPPMs by working closely with suppliers to ensure components met department quality standards.

Process Control

 Implement checklist, pokayokes and automatic controls to reduce process variability in the process and increase the yield from 60% to 98%.

Lean Manufacturing principles

• Implement 5S's, visual factory, process flow and kaizen events every 4 months.

Continuous improvement and cost reduction projects

• management of key projects to improve quality, scrap and efficiency, I saved \$250K in 2015.

Professional Experience

Sr Manufacturing Engineer

August 2015 Medtronic Inc. i1/4 District Of Columbia, DC

- As senior manufacturing engineer I support the final assembly area to meet the KPI's such as Safety, Scrap, efficiency, quality, material flow and continuous improvement.
- I get involved in projects of standardization and improvement of components to reduce product defects and improve product costs, also I have been a key player in the implementation of new products.

Process Improvement Engineer

November 2011 to August 2015 Arconic i¹/₄ Cleveland, OH

I perform the following activities: Coordinate the installation of liquid paint application & washer equipment Develop PFMEA & Control
plan for the new process Define the parameter chart for the new process(cure oven, application process amp; washer machine), Develop
process & procedures Define, design & require new fixtures for the process Define EPP & Safety practices for new paint process Define &
implement new layout Increase the FPY from 60% to 98% Implement scrap reduction projects(Recovery parts) Implement lean
accountability Continuous improvement projects / Cost Reduction (Scrap, Efficiency, Raw material) New Product Introduction team
member: Cost, process, routings, fixtures.

Process Engineer

May 2009 to November 2011 Cornerstone Building Brands il/4 Jasper, IN

- I performance in the following activities: As a part of a team we develop a VSM from all area to identify wastes and develop projects (Kaizen events) to eliminate them.
- I had 6 process inspector under my direction.
- Implementation of work Instructions and Visual Aids.
- PFMEA development.

- Supermarket implementation (Material flow project).
- Cost reduction projects (Material and Labor).
- 1st phase of Visual Factory implementation.
- Member of the New Product Introduction team developing the following activities:.
- Process Flow Diagrams Routing calculation.
- Fixture or new equipment needed Work instruction updated or create.
- Capability analysis for all areas under my responsibility.

Manufacturing Engineer

February 2005 to May 2009 Caterpillar il/4 Washington, IL

- I performance in the following activities: Set-Up and installation of new production lines(all facilities included).
- Cycle time analysis.
- Manufacturing lines optimization.
- Functional test for first articles.
- Design & Develop fixture to manufacturing lines.
- Review and update Bill of Materials (BOM) Elaborate internal ECN to change BOMs.
- I was part of the transition of new products from California to Nogales and from New York to Nogales.
- Capability analysis for warehouse.
- Capability analysis for fabrication areas.
- Implementation of FMEA in manufacturing lines.

Education and Training

Bachelor of Science: Indistrial Engineering, 2006 Institute Technological of Nogales i1/4 City, State, Mexico

Specialty in Quality and Productivity

Certifications

•GREEN BELT certification by ITESM Campus Sonora Norte.

(April 2014 â€" August 2014)

•LEAN MANUFACTURING certification by ITESM Campus Sonora Norte.

(February 2006 – July 2006)

•BASICS OF SUPPLY CHAIN MANAGEMENT certification by APICS.

(April 2007 – May 2007)

Languages

Bilingual:

Spanish 100%

English 80%.

Affiliations

No

Skills

ACADEMIC, AutoCAD, Continuous improvement, Cost Reduction, direction, ENGINEER, English, focus, Functional, Industrial Engineering, inspector, instruction, layout, Leadership, Lean Manufacturing, Lotus Notes, manufacturing engineer I, Materials, Microsoft Office, Microsoft Project, 98, optimization, paint, Problem solving, PROCESS ENGINEERING, improve product, quality, Routing, Safety, Bilingual Spanish, SUPPLY CHAIN MANAGEMENT, Teamwork, Telephone, VISIO.